# James Tymann

## Overview

Experienced team lead and software engineer with a passion for solving novel and interesting problems. Excited to dissect problems and find solutions that make products better. Strong web dev skills with a focus on backend and server structure and architecture.

# Work Experience

## The Social Edge

2016 to 2017 — Fullstack Developer — New York, NY

The Social Edge found their place in the market with a series of proof-of-concept prototypes. I was brought on to rearchitect their solutions so that they were stable, modern, and scalable.

#### Astrometrics

- · Architected a replacement to an existing tool that handles the processing, saving, and archiving of third party data and metrics.
- Built to scale so that the service can grow as the product grows without redesigning the system.
- Implemented real time data processing so data could be shown immediately on the product; all data was delayed using the old system.
- Provided data pipelines so that more services could analyze the dataset effectively and a-synchronously.
- Decreased data retrieval time so that larger sets of data can be analyzed.
- Enhancements allowed for easier integration of machine learning into our products.
- · Saved money by utilizing less expensive services that scale better. Saved hundreds on monthly hosting costs.

#### Contempo

- Upgraded a legacy PHP application to a Node/REST api backend and a standalone React/AltJS frontend.
- · Established continuous integration for easier environment management and software deploys.
- · Successfully launched the tool with complete feature coverage, including time saving enhancements for employees and customers.

#### Process Establishment

- Worked with the engineering team to come up with processes that met the team's work styles and needs.
- Implemented a version of scrum that solved for the team's planning and development needs.
- · Provided better team management, requirements elicitation, and communication to upper management about team priorities.

#### SQL Lessons

- The Social Edge's Sales and Media teams live and die by analyzing internal data and reports. The most important data is provided via regular reports and dashboard, however many teams craved more real time, or more in-depth data analysis.
- Taught SQL fundamentals classes so that teams could learn to access data directly and outside of the limitations of precompiled reports.
- · Teams used their new SQL knowledge to analyze data to finer degrees, discovering new sales techniques.

#### **Brand Networks**

2014 to 2016 — Product Architect — New York, NY 2013 to 2014 — Partner Engineer — New York, NY 2010 to 2013 — Senior Software Engineer — Rochester, NY

### #Momento - Product Architect

- Conceptualized and implemented a brand new social media activation for events.
- Designed an event activation experience that tackled a variety of problems: slow or intermittent internet access, non-technical on-site
  contractors needing to assemble and troubleshoot the product, and being robust enough to handle frequent shipping.
- Made \$250,000 in revenue in the first quarter of launch.
- Liaised with sales team to ensure product viability and establish pre-sales practices.

## Amex Open Forum - Lead Engineer

- Architected a new social media platform for small business owners.
- Worked directly with the client to both create a new product to meet their needs and simultaneously migrate a legacy product.
- · Successfully migrated and moved thousands of articles to a new theme and format with little to no impact on existing users and admins.
- Built a new social community for small business owners to share information.

#### American Express Offers - Lead Engineer

- Worked directly with Facebook and American Express to implement a system that provided users with individually tailored offers and deals.
- Implemented a joining of systems to create a new user experience.
- Product was featured in a national tv ad.

## Skills

Programming: Node / Javascript, HTML / CSS, C#, PHP, Java, CouchDB, MySQL, MSSQL Libraries and Frameworks: React, Flux, Angular, Bootstrap, jQuery, ASP.NET Hosting and Devices: AWS, Rackspace, Heroku, Android, Windows, Linux

## Education

BS in Software Engineering at Rochester Institute of Technology, Rochester, NY